<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.1" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="pi_zero2w" kind="page">
    <compoundname>pi_zero2w</compoundname>
    <title>Pi Zero 2 W Bring-Up</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><anchor id="pi_zero2w_1md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADix_OS_docs_public_pi_zero2w"/> RADix-OS now has the first pieces of the Raspberry Pi Zero 2 W port. Raspberry Pi firmware remains the real first-stage boot path: the GPU ROM, <computeroutput>bootcode.bin</computeroutput>, and <computeroutput>start4.elf</computeroutput> initialize RAM, read <computeroutput>config.txt</computeroutput>, load the ARM payload, and release the AArch64 cores. The RADix-specific second stage is optional, but it is still useful as a maintenance loader for future boot menus, kernel selection, reflash tools, handoff validation, and hardware policy.</para>
<para>The intended final shape is:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Pi firmware performs first-stage hardware boot.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A narrow Circle-based second-stage loader can load <computeroutput>RADIXKRN.IMG</computeroutput> from the FAT boot partition and jump through <computeroutput>rad_boot_handoff_t</computeroutput>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The standalone RADix payload uses the <computeroutput>bcm283x_pi</computeroutput> backend and does not link Circle.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<sect1 id="pi_zero2w_1autotoc_md40">
<title>Required Loader State</title>
<para>The handoff is intentionally strict for physical silicon. Before jumping from any second-stage loader to the RADix payload, the loader must:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Park secondary cores 1-3 in a clean <computeroutput>wfe</computeroutput> loop owned by the loader handoff.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Mask interrupts on core 0.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Disable the MMU and data cache.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Clean/invalidate data cache state covering the payload and handoff record.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Invalidate the instruction cache and TLB.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Jump to the RADix entry in AArch64 EL1.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<para><computeroutput><ref refid="radboot_8h_1aaf3d6ebb801a1c4ead09b3d4b7507c89" kindref="member">radboot_validate_handoff()</ref></computeroutput> rejects Pi handoff records that do not declare these conditions through the <computeroutput>RAD_BOOT_HANDOFF_FLAG_*</computeroutput> safety bits.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pi_zero2w_1autotoc_md41">
<title>Current Payload</title>
<para>Build the standalone payload with:</para>
<para><programlisting filename=".bash"><codeline><highlight class="normal">make<sp/>-C<sp/>tools/embedded/radix_pi_zero2w</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The output files are:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>tools/embedded/radix_pi_zero2w/RADIXKRN.ELF</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>tools/embedded/radix_pi_zero2w/RADIXKRN.IMG</computeroutput></para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Run the RADix-owned QEMU smoke test with:</para>
<para><programlisting filename=".bash"><codeline><highlight class="normal">tools/embedded/radix_pi_zero2w_smoke.sh</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The script uses <computeroutput>qemu-system-aarch64 -M raspi3b</computeroutput> because QEMU does not expose a Pi Zero 2 W machine model. If <computeroutput>qemu-system-aarch64</computeroutput> is not installed, the smoke test downloads and extracts Ubuntu&apos;s <computeroutput>qemu-system-arm</computeroutput> package under <computeroutput>.radbuild/qemu-arm</computeroutput> and reuses it on later runs. A passing run verifies the early BCM283x HAL, PL011 UART, mailbox framebuffer, handoff validation, payload entry, block and FAT mount scaffolds, USB/input scaffolds, framebuffer dirty present, A53 MMU/table setup, process/COW checks, and Slint/RADCompositor parity markers.</para>
<para>The current RAD-owned backend includes:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A platform split under <computeroutput>RADixKernel/platforms</computeroutput>: portable A53 code in <computeroutput>platforms/a53</computeroutput> and Pi-specific BCM283x drivers in <computeroutput>platforms/a53/bcm283x</computeroutput>.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>PL011 serial console registration.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>System timer reads and busy sleep.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Interrupt enable/disable hooks for the BCM interrupt controller.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Mailbox property framebuffer allocation and <computeroutput>/dev/fb0</computeroutput> registration.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>/dev/mmcblk0</computeroutput> block-device registration scaffold with in-memory sector backing for QEMU smoke reads.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>/dev/usb0</computeroutput> host-info scaffold and <computeroutput>/dev/input/event0</computeroutput> synthetic HID input event path.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A portable A53 MMU/process layer with 4 KiB translation-table construction, TTBR0 process roots, a TTBR1 kernel root, user-copy validation, COW page-fault handling, syscall dispatch framing, and kernel process-table fork/fd-clone/wait checks.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Slint/RADCompositor boot-shell, window-manager, terminal-window, and compositor-damage smoke markers.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pi_zero2w_1autotoc_md42">
<title>Circle Loader Gate</title>
<para>Run the combined loader/payload smoke test with:</para>
<para><programlisting filename=".bash"><codeline><highlight class="normal">tools/embedded/qemu_pizero2w_smoke.sh</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting></para>
<para>The Circle loader source now builds a narrow second-stage handoff record and emits loader-intent markers when serial output is visible. On this workstation the Circle image currently reaches QEMU without serial markers, so the combined smoke script treats the Circle image as a build gate and then runs the standalone RADix payload gate. Physical Pi hardware remains the next authority for validating the actual Circle FAT load and jump sequence.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pi_zero2w_1autotoc_md43">
<title>Current Limits</title>
<para>This page is experimental. The portable A53 layer now builds real page tables and enables the MMU in the standalone payload, but full EL0 ELF execution, preemptive user scheduling, and complete exec image replacement are still not at x86 parity. The eMMC, USB, HID, and Slint shell paths are still QEMU-visible scaffolds rather than complete physical drivers. The next Pi passes need the real BCM283x eMMC command engine, real DWC OTG host enumeration, hardware keyboard/mouse input, second-stage FAT load/jump validation on silicon, and full AArch64 userspace execution parity.</para>
<para>Physical Pi Zero 2 W hardware remains the authority for mailbox framebuffer and SD behavior. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/media/jvincent/Kingspec512/repos/RADix-OS/docs/public/pi-zero2w.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
