<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.1" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="crimson_status" kind="page">
    <compoundname>crimson_status</compoundname>
    <title>Crimson 0.1.0 Status</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><anchor id="crimson_status_1md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADix_OS_docs_public_crimson_status"/> Crimson 0.1.0 is an experimental beta line for RADix-OS. The branch goal is to stabilize the kernel-facing API, x86 VM smoke path, Slint shell integration, overlay binding, filesystem profile, and driver model enough for repeatable testing.</para>
<sect1 id="crimson_status_1autotoc_md15">
<title>Stable-Beta Surface</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Kernel lifecycle, printk, boot info, time, memory stats, and terminal commands.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Task, wait queue, mutex, event, timer, scheduler, and basic multicore reporting APIs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Device registry, ioctl encoding, input queues, framebuffer registration, TTY, PTY, block device, USB host-info, and VFS provider APIs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>I2C, SPI, DMA, module, IRQ, and overlay binding APIs.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>x86 GRUB VM smoke target with framebuffer shell, PTY/TTY terminal path, and clean no-journal ext4 read/write profile.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="crimson_status_1autotoc_md16">
<title>Experimental Surface</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>POSIX process and syscall coverage is usable for the current shell tests but not a complete Unix userspace contract.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Shared-memory <computeroutput>mmap</computeroutput>/<computeroutput>shm_open</computeroutput> support is present for the x86 compositor smoke path, but not yet a complete POSIX memory-mapping implementation.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>RADCompositor supports dirty-rectangle software composition and shm-backed producer surfaces; full Slint userspace apps and hardware page flip are still follow-up work.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Network APIs now include device/link/send/receive/poll shape, experimental IPv4/UDP datagram sockets, local TCP stream socket lifecycle support, and legacy virtio-net RX/TX queue ownership markers for the x86 VM target.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>RP2350 HSTX/DVI and SPI panel output are documented as framebuffer output goals, with backend completeness still target-dependent.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Pi Zero 2 W has an experimental standalone <computeroutput>bcm283x_pi</computeroutput> payload, handoff ABI, platform split under <computeroutput>platforms/a53</computeroutput>, PL011 serial path, timer reads, mailbox framebuffer path, SD block-device registration scaffold, USB/input scaffolds, portable A53 process/COW self-tests, and Slint/RADCompositor parity markers.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>DMA is available through the generic core and first consumed by SPI-style transfer paths.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="crimson_status_1autotoc_md17">
<title>Not Yet Complete</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Full POSIX userland compatibility, dynamic ELF loading, complete fork/exec semantics across every target, full ext4 journaling, USB stacks, PCIe, wire-level TCP, DHCP/DNS, and production networking are beyond the current Crimson beta surface.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The Pi Zero 2 W path still needs hardware-real Circle FAT loader jump validation, eMMC command implementation, DWC OTG USB host enumeration, hardware HID input, privileged AArch64 page-table/trap/user-entry/fork/exec/COW implementation, and Slint framebuffer rendering before it matches the x86 VM path. </para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/media/jvincent/Kingspec512/repos/RADix-OS/docs/public/crimson-status.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
