<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.1" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="radcompositor" kind="page">
    <compoundname>radcompositor</compoundname>
    <title>RADCompositor</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><anchor id="radcompositor_1md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADix_OS_docs_public_radcompositor"/> RADCompositor is an experimental Crimson 0.1.0 service for Slint-backed desktop composition. It is intentionally RADLib/RADix-owned: Slint renders each UI surface, but RADix owns the screen, window placement, z-order, input routing, and final framebuffer writes.</para>
<sect1 id="radcompositor_1autotoc_md40">
<title>Architecture</title>
<para>Each window-like UI surface renders into an off-screen pixel buffer. The compositor tracks damaged rectangles, copies the current front buffer forward into a software back buffer for those rectangles, redraws intersecting surfaces by z-order, and presents only the touched rectangles to the framebuffer backend. Surfaces may use opaque XRGB pixels or ARGB pixels with alpha blending.</para>
<para>The x86 VM target currently starts two Slint surfaces:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>RadDesktopSurface</computeroutput> for the desktop background, status, and applications menu.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>RadTerminalSurface</computeroutput> for the first terminal window backed by a RADix PTY.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Input events enter through the RADix input queue. Pointer coordinates are tested against compositor surface bounds in global screen space, translated into local surface coordinates, and then dispatched to the matching Slint window adapter.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="radcompositor_1autotoc_md41">
<title>Shared-Memory IPC</title>
<para>The x86 VM target exposes POSIX-inspired shared-memory syscalls for the first process-boundary compositor path. A userspace producer can create a shm object, map it with <computeroutput>mmap</computeroutput>, write pixels directly into that mapping, open <computeroutput>/dev/compositor0</computeroutput>, attach the shm fd as a compositor surface, and queue dirty rectangles with compositor ioctls.</para>
<para>This first producer path is intentionally small: <computeroutput>/bin/radgfx-smoke</computeroutput> maps a one-page XRGB surface and submits damage to prove that userspace pixels reach the compositor without copying through a pipe or PTY.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="radcompositor_1autotoc_md42">
<title>Current Limits</title>
<para>This path is still experimental. The boot desktop and terminal surfaces are trusted in-process objects, while the smoke producer is a separate process using shared pages. The x86 GRUB framebuffer still uses software shadow buffers rather than hardware page flip. Future passes should generalize shm-backed Slint applications, add damage extraction from Slint internals, add SIMD copy/blend backends, and make the cursor a compositor-managed surface.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="radcompositor_1autotoc_md43">
<title>Verification</title>
<para>The hosted Slint example and x86 VM smoke gate the compositor path with markers for surface creation, off-screen rendering, dirty queue submission, copy-forward, dirty framebuffer present, z-order, alpha blending, hit testing, input coordinate translation, and shared-memory process IPC. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/media/jvincent/Kingspec512/repos/RADix-OS/docs/public/radcompositor.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
