<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.1" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel" kind="page">
    <compoundname>md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel</compoundname>
    <title>RADEmbeddedKernel</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>RADEmbeddedKernel is RADLib&apos;s portable embedded kernel service layer. It gives bare-metal and simulator targets a small POSIX-like contract for tasks, events, time, VFS access, devices, bus transfers, audio devices, terminal commands, and memory accounting.</para>
<para>RADPx OS is now the main operating-system repository for x86 VM work, processes, POSIX compatibility, packageable services, and broader architecture ports. RADEmbeddedKernel remains useful as the RADLib-side embedded runtime module and as a source-compatible bridge for MCU-class and simple bare-metal targets.</para>
<para>The public interface is a C ABI with lightweight C++ wrappers. The C ABI is the stable boundary for future embedded plugins and for source-distributable HAL adapters. The C++ wrappers are convenience helpers for RADLib applications.</para>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md16">
<title>Backends</title>
<para><computeroutput>linux_sim</computeroutput> is the first functional backend. It maps kernel services to desktop threads, filesystems, clocks, mutexes, events, and fake devices so behavior can be validated in CI before hardware testing.</para>
<para><computeroutput>rp235x_pico</computeroutput> is the first MCU-class backend. It targets RP2350/RP2354 A/B Cortex-M33 devices through the Pico SDK, defaults to <computeroutput>PICO_BOARD=pico2</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>PICO_PLATFORM=rp2350-arm-s</computeroutput>, and is configured by RADLib&apos;s Python/JSON build flow before CMake is invoked.</para>
<para><computeroutput>circle_pi</computeroutput> is the first Raspberry Pi bare-metal backend. It targets Pi Zero 2 W through Circle and uses Circle&apos;s native Makefile flow for the smoke image. Circle remains optional; RADEmbeddedKernel is not architecturally tied to Circle.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md17">
<title>Service Model</title>
<para>The first-pass kernel surface includes:</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>task creation, join, yield, sleep, current task id, and task listing</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>mutex and event synchronization</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>monotonic time and sleep helpers</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>VFS mount/open/read/write/seek/stat/list APIs</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>typed device registry and dispatch</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>I2C, SPI, and audio control dispatch through registered devices</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>terminal command registration and built-in shell commands</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>memory allocation wrappers and memory usage counters</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>serial console attachment through <computeroutput>/dev/console</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>/dev/serial0</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>/dev/uart0</computeroutput>, and <computeroutput>/dev/ttyS0</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para>boot handoff records for board name, backend, console, SD mode, memory regions, and boot arguments</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>cooperative embedded run-loop APIs: <computeroutput><ref refid="radekernel_8h_1a924d9dcd4d6790a17ea5470015765c60" kindref="member">rad_kernel_poll()</ref></computeroutput>, <computeroutput><ref refid="radekernel_8h_1a44d4005c886d90ca5f2dbbdaa387e303" kindref="member">rad_kernel_run()</ref></computeroutput>, <computeroutput><ref refid="radekernel_8h_1aa4c16108a8634970040e1f04b8671a33" kindref="member">rad_kernel_request_shutdown()</ref></computeroutput>, and <computeroutput><ref refid="radekernel_8h_1ad17d72c80fd219707a8773f0f070f83b" kindref="member">rad_kernel_is_shutdown_requested()</ref></computeroutput></para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Built-in terminal commands include <computeroutput>help</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>tasks</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>mem</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>mounts</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>ls</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>cat</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>devices</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>time</computeroutput>, and <computeroutput>bootinfo</computeroutput>. On embedded backends, unsupported commands return <computeroutput>RAD_STATUS_NOT_SUPPORTED</computeroutput> instead of failing silently.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md18">
<title>RP235x Storage</title>
<para>RP235x normal VFS storage is SD-card only in this pass. Flash is intentionally not exposed as a normal writable filesystem. SPI SD is the conservative baseline path. Optional 4-bit PIO SDIO is exposed behind <computeroutput>RADEKERNEL_ENABLE_SDIO_PIO=ON</computeroutput> and <computeroutput>RADEKERNEL_SD_MODE=pio_sdio</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>auto</computeroutput>.</para>
<para>PIO SDIO requires correct board wiring: SD CLK, CMD, and four consecutive data GPIOs. The preferred integration candidate is <computeroutput>inindev/pico-fatfs-sd</computeroutput>, a trimmed RP2040/RP2350 FatFs SDIO/SPI driver with RP2350B GPIO support. The kernel exposes the HAL seam for this driver, but the external driver is not vendored into RADLib by default.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md19">
<title>Build Configuration</title>
<para>Embedded settings live in <computeroutput>buildconfig.json</computeroutput> under <computeroutput>embedded</computeroutput> and can be overridden by <computeroutput>build.py</computeroutput> flags. Committed defaults are intentionally portable: machine-local SDK, Circle, and toolchain paths should be supplied by local config, environment, or command-line flags instead of being committed.</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><computeroutput>pico_sdk_path</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>circle_root</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>toolchain_dir</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>pico_board</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>pico_platform</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>sd_mode</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>enable_sdio_pio</computeroutput></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><computeroutput>enable_psram</computeroutput></para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
<para><computeroutput>./build.py --build-embedded --embedded-target rp235x</computeroutput> configures the Pico SDK smoke project and emits the usual Pico artifacts when <computeroutput>arm-none-eabi</computeroutput> is available. <computeroutput>./build.py --build-embedded --embedded-target circle</computeroutput> builds the Circle Pi Zero 2 W smoke image when Circle and <computeroutput>aarch64-none-elf</computeroutput> are available.</para>
<para>RADpm package-manager development is separate from embedded HAL builds:</para>
<para><programlisting filename=".bash"><codeline><highlight class="normal">cmake<sp/>-S<sp/>.<sp/>-B<sp/>build-radpm<sp/>-DBUILD_RADPM_TOOL=ON<sp/>-DBUILD_RADUi=OFF</highlight></codeline>
<codeline><highlight class="normal">cmake<sp/>--build<sp/>build-radpm<sp/>--target<sp/>radpm</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md20">
<title>Embedded Portability</title>
<para>Small targets compile only the services they need and provide fixed-pool or static backing storage through the HAL. Pi-class and Zynq-class targets can enable the fuller VFS, terminal, and device registry model. MCU-class targets such as RP2040 and RP2350 start with time, events, device registry, bus dispatch, memory pools, serial shell, and SD-card VFS hooks.</para>
<para>The public headers and HAL adapter sources can be shared across ports, but the kernel archive itself must be built per architecture, ABI, and toolchain. A Cortex-M RP2350 build, a Cortex-A AArch64 Raspberry Pi build, and a Zynq A9 build cannot consume one universal static archive. They should instead ship as target-specific archives such as <computeroutput>libradekernel-rp2350-cortex-m33.a</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>libradekernel-aarch64-none-elf.a</computeroutput>, or <computeroutput>libradekernel-zynq-a9.a</computeroutput>, all exposing the same <computeroutput>radekernel</computeroutput> C ABI.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="md__media_jvincent_Kingspec512_repos_RADLib_docs_public_radembeddedkernel_1autotoc_md21">
<title>Current Limits</title>
<para>Dynamic ELF/plugin loading is not part of the first pass. The ABI is shaped so a future loader can pass a kernel API table to trusted plugins. User/kernel privilege separation is also out of scope for this preview; early embedded plugins and tasks should be treated as trusted code.</para>
<para>The RP235x boot shim is deliberately small: no filesystem, no dynamic allocation, and no shell. It prepares the boot handoff struct and jumps into the kernel entry path. The target budget is under 8 KiB of code and under 1 KiB of RAM for the shim. </para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="/media/jvincent/Kingspec512/repos/RADLib/docs/public/radembeddedkernel.md"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
